Guide to the William John Fielding Papers TAM.069
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
William John Fielding Papers
1911-1986
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Fielding, William J. (William John), 1886-1973
Kurzweil, Lester J.
TAM.069
4.5 Linear Feet in 4 record cartons, 1 manuscript box, and 1 folder
William Fielding (1886-1974) was an author, editor, and sexologist. He left school before completing the eighth grade and worked at various manual labor jobs. In 1906, he enrolled in bookkeeping and accounting courses, and in 1909 was hired as secretary for the Tiffany Company, from which he retired in 1963. Fielding served as a trustee for the Tiffany Foundation from 1946. By 1913, Fielding had articles published in the New York Call, a newspaper of the Socialist Party, and began taking classes at the Rand School of Social Science, also a socialist institution. He became interested in social problems and birth control and wrote a number of books and pamphlets on sexology and psychology. The collection contains correspondence, typescripts of Fielding's autobiography, All the Lives I Have Lived (Dorrance & Co., 1972), essays, reviews, poetry, and case histories. The case histories consist of correspondence with readers of Fielding's work in sexology and psychology who wrote to him for advice on personal matters, e.g., masturbation, homosexuality, transvestism, lesbians, birth control, impotence, frigidity, fetishes, nervous disorders and phobias. The correspondence series concerns Fielding's work at Tiffany's; his personal life and reflections; and his interest in and work relating to sexology, psychology, free thought, and other social issues.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by William John Fielding, 1974. The accession number associated with this gift is 1974.005.
One poster was found in the repository in 2014. The accession number associated with this material is 2014.161.
Historical/Biographical Note
William J. (William John) Fielding (1886-1974) was an author, editor, and sexologist. Born in New Jersey, he left school before completing the eighth grade and first worked in blast furnaces and then as a sandhog, boring tunnels under the Hudson River. In 1906, he decided to prepare for a clerical career rather than continuing hard manual labor. That same year, he enrolled in bookkeeping and accounting courses, and in 1909 was hired as secretary for the Tiffany Company. By 1913, Fielding had articles published in the New York Call and began taking classes at the Rand School of Social Science. He became interested in social problems and birth control and wrote a number of books and pamphlets on sexology and psychology, thirty of which were published over the years in the Little Blue Books series, including a thirteen-volume series, "Rational Sex" (Emanuel Haldeman-Julius, publisher). Fielding also published articles in The New York Call, the daily newspaper of the Socialist Party. He served as editor and literary editor of the Newark Leader (1915-22), as editor of Know Thyself (1913-24), and was active in Socialist Party politics in New Jersey throughout the 1920s. He also corresponded with Alfred Korzybski regarding the latter's theories of general semantics and mathematical reasoning. In 1942, Fielding was appointed secretary-treasurer of the Louis Comfort Tiffany Foundation, and in 1946 he became a trustee. Fielding retired from Tiffany in 1963 and published his autobiography All the Lives I Have Lived in 1972.
Chronology:
1908: Began his life-long relationship with Joseph Lewis
1909: Hired as secretary by George Heydt, then advertising manager for Tiffany Company.
1913-1915: Emanuel Haldeman-Julius was on the staff of the socialist newspaper, The New York Call and published articles by Fielding.
1914: Bought copies of The Woman Rebel by Margaret Sanger at an Emma Goldman meeting. As a grassroots supporter, he distributed copies of the book, and his writings began to reflect themes of social hygiene. By 1920, Joseph Lewis introduced Fielding to Dr. William J. Robinson, editor of Critic and Guide.
1914: George Heydt became secretary to the president and several vice-presidents at Tiffany and Fielding moved up the corporate ladder as Heydt's secretary
1918: Louis Comfort Tiffany Foundation formed
1913-late 1920s: Attended classes on economics, sociology and psychology at the Rand School, and participated in the Socialist Party politics in New Jersey.
1915-1918: Editor of the Newark Leader
1919-1930: The Little Blue Books were published by Emanuel Haldeman-Julius and gained wide popularity through mass distribution. Fielding contributed thirty titles to the series, including a thirteen-volume series on "Rational Sex" and other works in sexology and psychology.
1920: Introduced to A. Korzybski's theories of general semantics and mathematical reasoning.
1919-1922: literary editor of Newark Leader
1913-1924: editor of Know Thyself
1925: attended Sixth International Neo-Malthusian and Birth Control Conference as a member of the advisory council of the American Birth Control League
1933-1934: met Havelock Ellis and Norman Haire.
1942: Moved to Long Island. Appointed secretary-treasurer of the Louis Tiffany Foundation.
1946: Appointed trustee of the Tiffany Foundation
Late 1940's: Became involved with Ethical Humanism
1963: Retires from Tiffany.
1972: Publication of his autobiography, All the Lives I Have Lived (Dorrance and Co.).
Arrangement
The collection is organized into three series. Folders are arranged alphabetically.
Series I. Case Histories, 1923-1963
Series II. Correspondence, 1912-1986
Series III. Writings, 1911-1973 Series IV. Addendum, undated
Scope and Content Note
The papers contain correspondence; typescripts of Fielding's autobiography, All the Lives I Have Lived; essays, reviews, and poetry; and case histories from Fielding's work as a sexologist. The case histories consist of correspondence with readers of Fielding's work in sexology and psychology who wrote to him for advice on personal matters, e.g., masturbation, homosexuality, transvestism, lesbians, birth control, impotence, frigidity, fetishes, nervous disorders and phobias. The correspondence series, which comprises the majority of the collection, concerns Fielding's work at Tiffany's; his interest in and work relating to sexology, psychology, free thought, and other social issues; and his personal reflections. Prominent correspondents include Harry Benjamin, Havelock Ellis, Andre Fridon, E. Haldeman-Julius, Joseph Lewis, Alfred Korzybski, Martin J. Martin, Madalyn Murray O'Hair, William J. Robinson, Victor Robinson, Margaret Sanger, Samuel Schmalhausen and Marie C. Stopes. Notable organizations represented include the American Birth Control League, American Social Hygiene Association, Ethical Humanist Societies of Greater New York, Eugenics Educational Society, Freethinkers of America, Society for Constructive Birth Control (Great Britain), Thomas Paine Foundation, Thomas Paine Society, and Tiffany and Company. The collection reflects Fieldings diverse pursuits, clarifies the course of his career, and documents the personal history of an aging, middle-class individual living in America between 1960-1973.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Manuscripts (document genre); Correspondence.; Frigidity (Psychology); Transvestism |z United States.; Fetishism (Sexual behavior); Impotence; Homosexuality -- United States.; Free thought |z United States.; Birth control |z United States.; Eugenics |z United States; Manuscripts for publication.; Reviews (document genre); Photographs.; Case histories.; Autobiographies.; Sexology |z United States.; Sexologists |z United States.; Lesbians |z United States |x Case studies.; Lesbianism -- United States.; Humanistic ethics |z United States.; Homosexuality |z United States |x Case studies.; O'Hair, Madalyn Murray; Gilmartin, Daniel J.; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 -- Societies, etc.; Kurzweil, Lester J.; Ethical Humanist Societies of Greater New York; Society for Constructive Birth Control and Racial Progress (Great Britain); Eugenics Educational Society; Freethinkers of America; Robinson, Victor, 1886-1947; Korzybski, Alfred, 1879-1950; Lewis, Joseph, 1859-1939; Holmes, John Haynes, 1879-1964; Keller, Helen, 1880-1968.; Thomas Paine Foundation; Tiffany and Company; Thomas Paine Society; Bunche, Ralph J. (Ralph Johnson), 1904-1971; Fielding, William J. (William John), 1886-1973; Fulbright, J. William (James William), 1905-1995; Ellis, Havelock, 1859-1939; Haldeman-Julius, E. (Emanuel), 1888-1951; Goldwater, Barry M. (Barry Morris), 1909-1998; American Social Hygiene Association; American Birth Control League; Fielding, William J. (William John), 1886-1973
- Series I. Case Histories, 1923-1963; 465273
  Scope and Content Note
  Series I: Case Histories contains 49 case histories dated from 1923 to 1963. The case histories consist of correspondence with readers of Fielding's work in sexology and psychology who wrote to him for advice on personal matters (e.g. masturbation, homosexuality, transvestism, lesbians, birth control, impotence, frigidity, fetishes, nervous disorders and phobias), with Fielding's annotations.
  - Case Histories: List, undated; 465648 (Box 1, Folder 1A)
  - Case B1: B., W.E. / Age 50, 2 letters. SJF classifies as a "homosexual" but he is actually an active transvestite and potential transsexual. Contains description of lifestyle; desires to have children and questions surgical remedies, 1926; 465275 (Box 1, Folder 1B)
  - Case B1: Photographs (three photographs, one in men's and two in women's attire), 1926; 465784 (Box 5)
  - Case B2: B., E. F. / Age 18, masturbation., 1954; 465276 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Case B3: B., C. J. / Age 18, finds himself impotent after a physical injury; considers sex-gland transplantation to relieve condition but finds cost of operation prohibitive, 1928; 465277 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Case B4: B., F. A. / Age 19, what are the risks of pregnancy without penetration and explain the characteristics of spermatozoa, 1933; 465365 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Case B5: B., E. R. [re Blue Book on Homsexuality] / No age, commends WJF's book on homosexuality and asks that his name be left confidential, 1925; 465366 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Case C1: C., J. / "Very important Homosexual Case": narrative of JC's voyeurism re: his lesbian wife, his own interaction with male homosexuals and the suggestions of an acquaintance re: the institutionalization of homosexuals, 1923; 465367 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Case C2: C., A. M., 1921; 465368 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Case D1: D., R. / Male homosexual, details case history, wants information on European "clubs.", 1926; 465369 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Case D2: D., E., 1943; 465370 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Case E1: E., E. F. / Treatise on bisexuality; cross-tabulations of feminine and masculine characteristics, 1930; 465371 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Case E2: E., H. M. / Age 22, underdeveloped genitals, student at Annapolis, mentions fears of not fitting the military model (i.e., machismo), 1937; 465372 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Case F1: F., A. W. / Age 21, re: the evolution of his relationship with a woman; mutual masturbation and theories of the long term effects of coitus interruptus, 1935; 465374 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Case F2: F., D. / No age, Can anything increase the size of male reproductive organs?, 1947; 465375 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Case F3: F., C. / Minister, partial impotence, 1934; 465376 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Case F4: F., J. / re: The physiology of erection and stimulation, 1929; 465377 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Case F5: F., N. / Age 39, celibate all her life, daughter of prudish parents, now having an affair with a younger man, 1928; 465378 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Case G1: G., E. / Age 23, Idaho lesbian, lonely and doesn't know where to meet others of her kind, 1932; 465379 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Case G2: G., Mrs. I. / Married seven years but has never had an orgasm, has tolerated the sex act as a man's pleasure and undergone chemo-therapy, 1930; 465380 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Case G3: G., C.S. / No age, question regarding intercourse: specific distinction between copulation, fornication et al. terminology; ratio of penis to vagina size as related to women's pain, 1940; 465381 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Case H1: H., M. / Questions whether neurosis is hereditary because his girlfriends family is highly problematic, 1930; 465382 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Case J1: J., J. / Ejaculation precox, 1932; 465383 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Case K1: K., G. / Age 19, has never had intercourse with a woman and can't climax with women; masturbates; has become effeminate and threatens suicide, 1926; 465384 (Box 1, Folder 22A)
  - Case K2: K., R. A. / Case history of childhood development, Tridon's influence and socialism, 1924; 465385 (Box 1, Folder 22B)
  - Case L1: L., C. / Age 23, 2 letters. Homosexual who wants to be 'normal'; happily married; describes masturbatory behavior, lack of attraction to women and fetish for fully dressed males with their fingernails exposed, 1928; 465386 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Case L2: L., Henry B. / Age 29, illness for 3.5 years has plagued him with numerous symptoms and diagnosis (frequent urination, glycosurea, stomach disorders, lost spirit), 1925; 465387 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Case L3: L., W. / Homosexual, "Uranian type"; wants to meet others of his class; encloses photo of himself with typed verse by "Riley" on back, 1929; 465388 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Case M1: Mrs. C. M. / Young married woman with phobia of looking people in the eyes, undated; 465389 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Case M2: M., C. / Age 65, married, describes wife's Oedipal condition. (WJF seems to have misclassified this as "Homosexuality case"), 1923; 465390 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Case N1: N., H. J. / Homosexual, recounts childhood recollections, masturbation, nocturnal emission in sleep, 'heat attacks' of the prostrate glands, 1930; 465391 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Case P1; P., G. / Age early 60's, symptoms of neurasthenia and anxiety neurosis, 1945; 465392 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Case P2: P., S. / re: Myths of masturbation, 1929; 465393 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Case P3: P., C. D. / Attorney writing for an anonymous woman client, re: masturbation, 1940; 465394 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Case P4: P., W.E. / re: WJF's publication of an incorrect astronomical statement, 1930; 465395 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Case P5: "Men Who Make Passes" [at women]: Clipping, 1933; 465396 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Case R1: R., B. N. / Age 39, is pregnancy advisable at her age?; is there any way to postpone menopause?, 1930; 465397 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Case R2: R., R. / Age 25, what effects does coitus interruptus have over a prolonged period of time?; will his penis be rendered useless?, 1932; 465398 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Case R3: R., Mrs. H. E. / Life history; phobias of marriage, snakes; relation with mother; had withdrawn from work, 1923; 465399 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Case S1: S., A. / Age 26, anxiety and sexual neurosis; mental and physical masturbation, has never been "with" a woman but is engaged to be married, 1926; 465400 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Case S2: S., E. C. / Age 42, divorced, series of sex questions re: his ex-wife's abortions and coldness to him, coitus interruptus, condoms, 1925; 465401 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Case S3: S., S. / b. 1898, childhood sexuality, masturbation, excessive periods of depression, doesn't know if he's fit for marriage, 1925; 465402 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Case S4: S., M. E. / No age, questions re: reproductive anatomy; includes diagrammatic reply from WJF, 1939; 465403 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Case Histories: S5 S., V. Contents: a "specialist" recommended that he abstain from sex and practice masturbation to relieve illness, 1931; 465404 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Case S6: S., J. / Complaints of large, loosely suspended testicles; WJF recommends cold water sitz baths before and after sex, 1936; 465405 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Case S7: S., A. J. / Fears that he will not be able to have simultaneous orgasms with his future wife, 1932; 465406 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Case T1: T., D. / Age 24, male homosexual, pacifist, socialist, lonely, loves children, 1938; 465407 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Case W1: W., W., 1931; 465408 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Case W2: W., R. J. / Re: the future of psychiatry as a profession, 1933; 465409 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Case Y1: Y., G. V. / Found WJF's Little Blue Book on menopause extremely enlightening, 1927; 465410 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Case Z1: Z., I. / Age 24, married, no children; unable to have orgasm. Must a woman discharge at the same time as the male discharges seminal fluid in order to conceive?, 1931; 465411 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Original Case Histories, 1923-1963; 466101 (Box 5)
- Series II. Correspondence, 1912-1986; 465448
  The bulk of Series II: Correspondence consists of personal correspondence between Fielding and less famous colleagues, readers, researchers, and friends. In his later years, these provide summaries of his career that are more personal than his autobiography, including letters that describe Fielding's struggle with emphysema and arthritis and his wife's affliction with cerebral artereo-sclerosis. Fielding also had personal correspondence with well-known individuals like Upton Sinclair (1918-1928), John Haynes Holmes (1938), Ralph Bunche (1955) and J. W. Fulbright (1965). Scattered throughout is printed ephemera relating to sexology, psychology, and other matters.
  This series also documents Fielding's participation in the American Social Hygiene Association, The American Birth Control League, the Eugenics Educational Society, the Society for Constructive Birth Control and Racial Progress, the Ethical Humanist Societies of Greater New York, the Freethinkers of America, and the Thomas Paine Foundation through correspondence with officials and members of these organizations. Among Fielding's correspondents in the Birth Control, Sexual Reform and Psychology movements between 1917 and 1972 were Drs. William J. Robinson, Harry Benjamin, Victor Robinson, Samuel Schmalhausen, and Andre Tridon. Other correspondents include Marie C. Stopes, Margaret Sanger, and Havelock Ellis. His relationship with Emanuel Haldmann-Julius, owner and editor of the Little Blue Books, is evident in correspondence with Haldmann-Julius, his family, and his biographers (1919-1973). Issues of free thought and rationalism are discussed in correspondence with Joseph Lewis (1923-1968), Alfred Korzybski (on general semantics and mathematical reasoning, 1921-1933), Martin J. Martin (1966-1971), and Madalyn Murray O'Hair (1969-1971).
  Fielding's expertise in Tiffany artworks and the history of the Tiffany firm generated considerable correspondence with collectors and other parties interested in the authenticity of pieces and his own collection. Fielding's employment at Tiffany's also placed him in the position of ex-officio income tax consultant for the company's executives and for Emelia Tiffany. Letters from John D. Rockefeller (1922), Helen Keller (1928), and Barry Goldwater (1959) were acquired through his affiliation with Tiffany.
  This series also includes a small number of photographs, likely removed from Fielding's personal correspondence.
  - Clippings, 1935-1969; 465412 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Correspondence: "A", 1920-1972; 465413 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Correspondence: Ackerson, John, 1968-1972; 465414 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Correspondence: Ackley, Sheldon and Helen, 1951-1972; 465415 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Correspondence: American Ethical Union, 1964-1968; 465416 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Correspondence: American Humanist Association, 1968-1971; 465417 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Correspondence: American Rationalist, 1964-1973; 465418 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Correspondence: American Social Hygiene Association, 1920; 465419 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Correspondence: "B", 1927-1973; 465420 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Correspondence: Baird, William, 1971-1972; 465421 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Correspondence: Barad, Emil and Lillian, 1968-1971; 465422 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Correspondence: Beals, Sarita, 1953; 465423 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Correspondence: Benjamin, Harry, 1934-1972; 465424 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Correspondence: Benjamin, Jack, 1970-1973; 465425 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Correspondence: Biersted, Sonja, 1969-1972; 465426 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Correspondence: Borgstede, Margaret, 1963-1970; 465427 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Correspondence: Brown, Hugh A., 1963-1972; 465428 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Correspondence: Burns, Ann, Sep-Oct 1968; 465429 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Correspondence: "C", 1921-1972; 465430 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Correspondence: Cameron, William and Molly, 1942-1972; 465431 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Correspondence: Cancialdi, Lewis, 1950-1972; 465432 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Correspondence: The Churchman, 1970-1972; 465433 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Correspondence: Copeland, Faye, 1949-1968; 465434 (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Correspondence: Cummings, Robert, 1968; 465435 (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Correspondence: "D", 1919-1967; 465436 (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - Correspondence: Daniels, Dr. Ann, 1955-1963; 465437 (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - Correspondence: De Gruson, Gere [Curator, Haldeman-Julius Collection], 1970-1972; 465438 (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - Correspondence: Dodd, Mead and Co., 1958-1970; 465439 (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - Correspondence: Dorbin, Arthur (Ethical Humanist Society of Long Island), 1958-1972; 465440 (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - Correspondence: Dorrance and Co. [Publisher of Fielding Autobiography], 1921-1973; 465441 (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - Correspondence: Dunn, James, 1957-1971; 465442 (Box 1, Folder 79)
  - Correspondence: "E", 1918-1970; 465443 (Box 1, Folder 80)
  - Correspondence: Ellis, Havelock, 1927-1934; 465444 (Box 1, Folder 81)
  - Correspondence: Ericson, Edward, 1964-1968; 465445 (Box 1, Folder 82)
  - Correspondence: Ethical Culture Society of Long Island, 1955-1969; 465446 (Box 1, Folder 83)
  - Correspondence: Euthanasia Educational Fund, Inc., 1972; 465447 (Box 1, Folder 84)
  - Correspondence: Euthanasia Society of America, Inc., 1940-1967; 465449 (Box 1, Folder 85)
  - Correspondence: "F", 1920-1972; 465450 (Box 1, Folder 86)
  - Correspondence: Fielding Family and Personal, 1949-1973; 465451 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: Fielding Family and Personal, Business and Medical, 1955-1986; 465472 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: Fielding Family and Personal: Kurzweil, Lester Esq., 1970; 465473 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: Fielding Family and Personal: Mesh Family, 1964-1971; 465474 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence: Fielding Family and Personal: Pastore, Evelyn and Pat, 1969; 465475 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: Fielding Family and Personal: Reber Family, 1967-1972; 465476 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: Fielding Family and Personal: Rothstein, Dr. Daniel, 1964-1969; 465477 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: Fielding Family and Personal: Thomas, Elsie and Gladys Otto, 1954-1972; 465478 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence: Fielding Family and Personal: Zampano, Janet and Frank, 1967-1969; 465479 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence: Franklin, Dr. Leo, 1936; 465480 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence: "G", 1919-1973; 465481 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence: "H", 1916-1972; 465482 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence: Haldeman, Henry, 1966-1967; 465483 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence: Haldeman-Julius, Emanuel, 1919-1951; 465484 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence: Haldman-Julius, Sue, 1925, 1961-1974; 465485 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence: Harder, Fred, 1951-1958; 465486 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence: Hart, Charles, 1952-1966; 465487 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence: Hendrie, William, 1966-1969; 465488 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence: Herder, Dale. M., 1971-1973; 465489 (Box 2, Folder 19)